Hello, welcome to Career 247. I am
नमस्कार वेलकम टू करियर 247 मैं हूं
Prashant Dhawan. Now, this video is being
प्रशांत धवन नाउ यह वीडियो आज के समय पूरी
seen all over the world today. Many people are feeling
दुनिया में देखी जा रही है कई लोग यह
scared about their flight after watching this video,
वीडियो देखकर अपनी फ्लाइट को लेकर डर
because the way
महसूस कर रहे हैं क्योंकि जिस तरीके से
this Air India
भारत के गुजरात राज्य में यह एयर इंडिया
flight, a Boeing Dreamliner 787, has crashed in the Indian state of Gujarat.
की फ्लाइट एक बोइंग ड्रीमलाइनर 787 क्रैश
This is horrifying. The
हुआ है दिस इज हॉररिफाइंग जो विजुअल्स
visuals that have come out are being seen by the entire world. I have
सामने आए हैं पूरी दुनिया यह विजुअल्स देख
many friends who are in Europe
रही है मेरे कई कई मित्र हैं जो यूरोप में
, in the US.  Seeing these visuals, it
हैं, यूएस में हैं। यह विजुअल्स देखकर
suddenly came to his mind that there is suddenly anxiety about our
सडनली उनके माइंड में आ गया कि हमारी जो
flights in the future.
फ्लाइट्स है इन द फ्यूचर उसको लेकर अब
Because the
अचानक से एंग्जायटी हो गई है। क्योंकि जिस
way this flight has crashed, no one is able to
तरीके से यह फ्लाइट क्रैश करी है ना किसी
understand what exactly has happened here.
को समझ नहीं आ रहा कि आखिर यहां पे हुआ
Because if you see the route of this flight,
क्या है। क्योंकि आप इस फ्लाइट का रूट
you will be able to see it from Ahmedabad city of Gujarat.  This is Ahmedabad airport.
इधर आप देख पाओगे। यह अहमदाबाद एयरपोर्ट
This flight took off from here and
है। यहां से यह फ्लाइट टेक ऑफ करती है और
its route was London.  This flight was to go to the UK.  It
इसका रूट था लंदन। यूके में इस फ्लाइट को
was a long journey.  Now now I will
जाना था। लंबी जर्नी थी। नाउ अब मुझको
have to mention this here also.  When there is an
यहां पर यह भी मेंशन करना पड़ेगा। जब
international journey in a big
इंटरनेशनल जर्नी होती है ना किसी बड़े
aircraft, then a lot of fuel is also
विमान की तब उसमें फ्यूल भी बहुत सारा
carried in it.  And suppose such a
कैरी किया जाता है। और अगर मान लीजिए ऐसी
flight crashes, then since it was
फ्लाइट जब गिरती है तो फ्यूल सिंस वो बहुत
carrying a lot of extra fuel, the explosion that
ज्यादा एक्स्ट्रा कैरी कर रही थी जो धमाका
occurs is all the more
जो एक्सप्लोजन होता है वो और ज्यादा
painful.  So right now you are
दर्दनाक होता है। तो अभी जो आप ये
seeing these visuals, you are watching the videos in front of you.
विजुअल्स देख रहे हैं अपने सामने वीडियोस
If you are wondering
देख रहे हैं। अगर आप सोच रहे हैं कि इतना
how such a big explosion happened?  So see, this flight was
बड़ा धमाका कैसे हो गया? तो यह फ्लाइट
going carrying fuel.  That would
देखिए फ्यूल कैरी करके जा रही थी। दैट वुड
take it all the way to London.  And if
टेक इट ऑल द वे टू लंदन। और अगर यहां पर
you people here are thinking, wait, this flight was
आप लोग सोच रहे हैं वेट यह फ्लाइट गुजरात
going from Gujarat to UK and it crashed in Gujarat itself.
से यूके जाने वाली थी और गुजरात में ही
See,
क्रैश कर गई। देखिए बिल्कुल अहमदाबाद
this flight suddenly crashes just a short distance away from Ahmedabad airport.  The
एयरपोर्ट से कुछ ही दूर यह फ्लाइट अचानक
pilots here had more
से क्रैश कर जाती है। जो पायलट थे यहां पर
than 8000 hours of experience.
इनको 8000 घंटे से भी जरा का एक्सपीरियंस
No one understands what
था। नो वन अंडरस्टैंड्स कि अचानक से क्या
happened suddenly that after travelling a short distance this airplane just
हुआ कि कुछ ही दूर जाकर यह एयरप्लेन बस
crashes.  A huge explosion occurs.
क्रैश कर जाता है। एक बड़ा धमाका होता है।
And the unfortunate thing is that there were a
और अनफॉर्चूनेट बात देखिए इस प्लेन में
total of 242 passengers in this plane who belonged to different countries.
टोटल 242 पैसेंजर्स थे जो विभिन्न देशों
If you look at Air India's
को बिलोंग करते हैं। आप अगर एयर इंडिया का
Twitter page, everything has been
Twitter पेज देखोगे ना आज के समय सब कुछ
blacked out today.  Profile photo banner
ब्लैक कर दिया गया है। प्रोफाइल फोटो बैनर
everything because this is a big accident.  If
सब कुछ क्योंकि यह एक बड़ा हादसा है। अगर
I talk about intensity, then
मैं अगर बात करूं इंटेंसिटी की तो 15
this is the biggest air accident in the last 15 years
सालों में सबसे बड़ा एयर एक्सीडेंट है ये
in the history of India. It is possible that this may
भारत के इतिहास में हो सकता है कि ये 25
also become the biggest accident in 25 years if the
साल का सबसे बड़ा एक्सीडेंट भी हो जाए अगर
casualties here cross 150 or
यहां पे जो कैजुअल्टीज है ये 150 या फिर
160.  The last time the country
160 को ही पार कर जाती है। आखिरी बार देश
saw an airplane disaster of this level was in 2010 when unfortunately
देखा था साल 2010 में जब अनफॉर्चुनेटली
158 people died.  It is not yet confirmed where
158 लोगों की मौत हुई थी। अभी तक कंफर्म
Air India Flight 171
नहीं है कि एयर इंडिया फ्लाइट 171 जो
crashed here in Gujarat.
क्रैश करी है यहां पर गुजरात में। यहां पर
How many people have died here?  But Air India has
कितने लोगों की मौत हुई है? बट एयर इंडिया
blacked out its social media handles everywhere.  And below these people have
ब्लैक कर दिया है। और नीचे इन लोगों ने
confirmed the nationality of the passengers.  There were 168
पैसेंजर्स की नेशनलिटी कंफर्म करी है। 168
Indians here and 53 British
थे यहां पर इंडियन 53 थे यहां पर ब्रिटिश
nationals here.  Was a Canadian National.  There
नेशनल्स। एक कनेडियन नेशनल था। सात
were seven Portuguese here.  So
पोर्तुगीज़ थे यहां पर। तो इस इंसिडेंट को
look at this incident, whatever investigation will be done, most
लेकर देखिए जो भी जांच पड़ताल होगी मोस्ट
likely UK, Portugal, even
प्रोबब्ली इसमें यूके, पोर्तुगल इवन
Canadian governments may get
कनेडियन गवर्नमेंट हो सकता है कि यहां पर
involved and look online, there are
इन्वॉल्व हो जाए और ऑनलाइन देखिए आज के
a lot of theories going around today.  Some are
समय बहुत सारी थ्योरीज चल रही है। कोई कह
saying that it was sabotage.  Something has happened etc.
रहा है कि यह सबोटाज किया गया था। कुछ हुआ
No one knows, until the black box of the plane is
है वगैरह नो वन नोज़ जब तक प्लेन का ब्लैक
found, we will
बॉक्स नहीं मिलता तब तक हमको प्रॉपर यहां
not get proper information about what happened and
पे जानकारी मिलेगी नहीं कि हुआ क्या था और
many people were also asking this question
कई लोग वैसे यह भी सवाल पूछ रहे थे कि
whether former Chief Minister of Gujarat Vijay
क्या गुजरात के फॉर्मर चीफ मिनिस्टर विजय
Rupani was also present here, so the answer to this is yes,
रूपाणी भी यहां पर थे तो इसका आंसर है हां
ex-Chief Minister of Gujarat was also here
गुजरात के एक्स चीफ मिनिस्टर भी यहां पर
and some reports are claiming that
थे और कुछ रिपोर्ट्स क्लेम कर रही है कि
his name is also there in the casualties, again the
कैजुअल्टीज में इनका भी नाम है अगेन कितने
actual number of how many people have died here is
लोग यहां पर मारे गए हैं इसका एक्चुअल
not out yet because many people are also
नंबर अभी आया नहीं है क्योंकि कई लोग बुरी
badly injured here and I will
तरीके से इंजर्ड भी हैं यहां पर और मुझको
also have to tell you that in these images that you are seeing,
यह भी बोलना पड़ेगा आप जो यह इमेजेस देख
where did this plane crash
रहे हैं ना कि यह प्लेन क्रैश कहां पे
?  This building is a
किया था? यह जो बिल्डिंग है यह एक
doctor's hostel.  Many people are saying
डॉक्टर्स हॉस्टल की है। कई लोग कह रहे हैं
that yes, this was a hospital.  No,
कि जी यह हॉस्पिटल था। नहीं डॉक्टर्स के
a hostel had been built for doctors.  After reaching there,
लिए एक हॉस्टल बना रखा था। वहां पे जाकर
the plane crashed on its roof.  15
उसकी छत पर यह प्लेन क्रैश हुआ है। 15
doctors who lived here have also been seriously
डॉक्टर जो यहां पर रहते थे वो भी बुरी
injured.  Again this is a
तरीके से इंजर हुए हैं। अगेन दिस इज अ
tragedy.  This is perhaps it will be mentioned as
ट्रेजडी। दिस इज़ परहैप्स इंडिया की
one of the biggest tragedies that has happened in the history of India.
हिस्ट्री में जो वन ऑफ द बिगेस्ट ट्रेजडीज
And the
हुई हैं उनमें इसको मेंशन किया जाएगा। और
world is also watching this tragedy
दुनिया भी इस ट्रेजडी को इसलिए देख रही है
because this is the first time that Boeing's 787
क्योंकि यह पहली बार है जब बोइंग का 787
Dreamliner, which is considered to be their best plane, has
ड्रीम लाइनर जो इनका सबसे बेहतरीन प्लेन
crashed
माना जाता है पहली बार इसका क्रैश हुआ है
and these are the images in front of you of the
और यह आपके सामने इमेजेस हैं हॉस्टल के
inside of the hostel, where doctors were having their food,
अंदर की जो यहां पे डॉक्टर्स खाना खा रहे
some were resting, suddenly a Boeing
थे कुछ रेस्ट कर रहे थे अचानक से एक बोइंग
787 comes with a lot of fuel and there is a huge
7 87 आता है बहुत सारे फ्यूल के साथ बड़ा
blast, people get badly injured, the
ब्लास्ट होता है लोग बुरी तरीके से इंजर
more I read about this accident
हो जाते हैं जितना पढ़ता हूं इस हादसे के
the more sad my heart becomes
बारे में दिल उतना ज्यादा उदास हो जाता है
and if we compare this accident with other global
और अगर इस हाद हादसे को हम बाकी ग्लोबल
disasters, you will note a pattern.
डिजास्टर से कंपेयर करें तो आप एक पैटर्न
Recently, look around the world,
नोट करोगे। रिसेंटली देखिए दुनिया भर में
many of Boeing's planes have
बोइंग के बहुत सारे जो यह प्लेेंस हैं यह
crashed one by one and people have
एक-एक करके क्रैश किए हैं और लोगों ने
often
काफी बार बोइंग के एयरप्लेेंस की क्वालिटी
raised questions on the quality of Boeing airplanes.  Now
पर भी सवाल उठाए हैं। अब इस पर्टिकुलर केस
what has happened in this particular case?  Has something been sabotaged
में क्या हुआ है? क्या कुछ साबोटाज किया
?  Is there some conspiracy?  Was there some
गया है? कुछ षड्यंत्र हुआ है? यहां पे कुछ
engine fault here?  I will tell you this again.  Don't
इंजन का फॉल्ट था? यह अगेन मैं आपको
speculate about this right now.
बोलूंगा। अभी स्पेकुलेशन मत करिएगा इसको
Details of the black box would be being extracted at this time.
लेकर। ब्लैक बॉक्स की डिटेल्स इस वक्त
Very soon we will
निकाली जा रही होंगी। बहुत ही जल्द हमको
know what happened here.  But
पता लग जाएगा कि यहां पर हुआ क्या था। बट
either way this is another crash of a Boeing airplane
इदर वे यह एक और बोइंग एयरप्लेन का क्रैश
which has happened within a gap of just a few months.
है जो कुछ ही महीने के इंटरवल में हुआ है।
Before this, you will remember that in December 2024,
इससे पहले आपको याद होगा दिसंबर 2024 में
literally on 29th December 2024, there was a South Korean
लिटरली 29 दिसंबर 2024 में एक साउथ कोरियन
flight Jeju Air 2216 which
फ्लाइट थी जेजू एयर की 2216 यह बुरी तरीके
crashed badly.  94 people lost their lives.
से क्रैश कर गई। 94 लोगों को अपनी जान
Boeing officially
गवानी पड़ी। बोइंग ने ऑफिशियली कंडोलेंसेस
offered its condolences, saying what has happened is very bad.
अपनी दी कि देखिए यह जो हुआ है बहुत बुरा
Now the actual reason for the crash of this flight has
हुआ है। नाउ इस फ्लाइट के गिरने का जो
not been revealed till date.
एक्चुअल रीजन है यह आज तक सामने आया नहीं।
Some people say, look, those birds, those
कुछ लोग कहते हैं कि जी देखिए जो बर्ड्स
ducks, were stuck in the engine.
है जो डक्स हैं वो इंजन में फंस गई थी।
Because of that the engine stopped again and it
उसकी वजह से इंजन फिर बंद हो गया और यह
crashed.  This is very rare
क्रैश कर गया। यह बहुत ज्यादा रेयर होता
and even when the black box was studied, no
है और इवन जब ब्लैक बॉक्स को स्टडी किया
proper information was found as to
गया तो कोई प्रॉपर यहां पे जानकारी मिली
why this plane crashed
नहीं कि यह प्लेन आखिर क्रैश हुआ क्यों है
and apart from that, if you observe,
और उसके अलावा भी आप अगर देखोगे तो 2024
in 2024, Boeing's plane constantly
में कास्टेंटली बोइंग का प्लेन कहीं ना
remains in the news somewhere or the other.  It is not necessary
कहीं न्यूज़ में रहता है। जरूरी नहीं है
that every time a G crashes and you know
कि हर बार जी क्रैश हो गया और यू नो 100
100-200 people get killed.  Many times this plane suddenly performs a
200 लोग मारे गए। कई बार यह प्लेन अचानक
malfunction.  All that is heard in the news is that
से माल फंक्शन कर देता है। न्यूज़ में यही
look, the plane has skidded
आता है कि देखिए जो प्लेन है स्किट कर गया
or some other problem has occurred here.   There was
या फिर कुछ और प्रॉब्लम्स यहां पर आ गई।
some severe turbulence.  But
कुछ सीवियर टर्बुलेंस हो गई। बट
constantly we are seeing that
कास्टेंटली हम यह देख रहे हैं कि बोइंग
these instances related to Boeing planes are
प्लेन से रिलेटेड जो यह इंस्टेंसेस हैं,
increasing.  And I would
यह बढ़ते जा रहे हैं। और यह कोई मैं
say that it is not a small thing that
कहूंगा छोटी बात नहीं है कि कुछ ही महीनों
in the span of just a few months, two big flights, a South Korean flight and
के अंतराल में एक साउथ कोरियन फ्लाइट और
now an Indian flight, have
अब एक इंडियन फ्लाइट दो बड़ी फ्लाइट्स
crashed and many people have lost their
क्रैश हुई है और बहुत से लोगों की यहां पर
lives here and after this crash in Gujarat,
जान गई है और गुजरात के इस क्रैश के बाद
in the times to come you will see that
आने वाले समय में आप देखोगे भारत में जो
this name John Barnett will be discussed a lot in India.
यह नाम है ना जॉन बारनेट इसकी काफी चर्चा
He was a whistle blower.  He
होगी। यह एक विसल ब्लोअर थे। इन्होंने 30
worked at Boeing for 30 years as a quality
साल तक बोइंग में काम किया एस क्वालिटी
manager.
मैनेजर।
In 2019, he gave an interview to BBC
2019 में इन्होंने बीबीसी को एक इंटरव्यू
and openly said that all the
दिया और खुलकर बोल दिया कि देखिए बोइंग
planes being made in Boeing are
में जो प्लेन बनाए जा रहे हैं यह सब
standard.  These people
स्टैंडर्ड हैं। जो यहां पर पार्ट्स ये लोग
use these parts in many places.  These are of very
काफी जगह यूज़ करते हैं। यह बहुत ज्यादा
poor quality.  Here you will be able to see
खराब क्वालिटी के हैं। इधर आप देख पाओगे
these 2019 Barnet Claims that Workers were
इन 2019 बारnट क्लेम दैट वर्कर्स वर
Forced.  Literally, workers often used to
फोर्स्ड। लिटरली वर्कर्स काफी बार जब
say that the parts we are installing
बोलते थे ना कि यह जो पार्ट्स हम इंस्टॉल
in Boeing 787 are of very
कर रहे हैं बोइंग के 787 में बहुत ज्यादा
poor quality.  There might be a problem tomorrow.
खराब क्वालिटी के हैं। कल को प्रॉब्लम आ
Then pressure was put on them to
सकती है। तब उन पर प्रेशर डाला जाता था कि
meet the deadline.  Production has to be increased.  The
डेडलाइन मीट करनी है। प्रोडक्शन बढ़ानी
company needs profit.  So somehow by
है। कंपनी को प्रॉफिट चाहिए। तो कैसे भी
adding crooked parts they
करके टेढ़े-मेढ़े पार्ट्स डालकर इन्होंने
sent the Boeing Dream Liner forward for production, you know.  And they had
प्रोडक्शन के लिए भेज दिया। और इन्होंने
pointed out many issues that the
बहुत सारे इशूज़ पॉइंट आउट किए थे कि जो
emergency oxygen system in Boeing 787
इमरजेंसी ऑक्सीजन सिस्टम है बोइंग 787 में
can fail during the flight.  And
यह फेल कर सकते हैं फ्लाइट के दौरान। और
Boeing's stock suffered huge losses.  Because
बोइंग के स्टॉक को काफी लॉस हुआ था। बिकॉज़
of John Bard.  You can say that he caused a
ऑफ जॉन बार्ड। आप कह सकते हैं इन्होंने
loss of millions to Boeing.
मिलियंस का नुकसान कर दिया था बोइंग का।
Now what happens suddenly?  He
अब अचानक से क्या होता है? इन्होंने बोइंग
exposed Boeing.  Suddenly after a few years he gets
की पोल खोल दी। सडनली कुछ साल बाद यह
killed in mysterious circumstances.  Was
मिस्टीरियस सरकमस्ट्ससेस में मारे जाते
sitting alone in my house.  He
हैं। अकेले अपने घर में बैठे हुए थे। बिना
shot himself without any reason and his family has
वजह खुद को गोली मार दी और इनकी फैमिली ने
recently filed a case against Boeing.  His
रिसेंटली बोइंग पर केस किया है। इनकी
family has said that John Barnett was subjected to a sustained
फैमिली ने कहा है कि जॉन बारनेट पर लगातार
campaign of harassment.  There was a
कैंपेन ऑफ हरासमेंट किया गया था। था
resolution when they raised
हिमिलेशन किया गया था जब इन्होंने रेज किए
concerns about safety issues, so look at the present time,
कंसर्न्स अबाउट सेफ्टी इशज़ तो आज का समय
in India too, the warnings given by John Barnett will be
देखिए भारत में भी जॉन बारनेट की जो
read and studied
वार्निंग्स थी उनको पढ़ा जाएगा स्टडी किया
and perhaps now the time has come that we should
जाएगा और परहैप्स अब टाइम आ चुका है कि हम
also see whether India has an
इस बात को भी देखें कि क्या भारत के पास
alternative to commercial airlines
अल्टरनेटिव है कमर्शियल एयरलाइंस का
because if you think about it, we are completely
क्योंकि आप अगर सोच कर देखो हम कंप्लीटली
dependent on the western world
डिपेंडेंट है वेस्टर्न वर्ल्ड पर अपनी
for our flights, whatever airplanes we have
फ्लाइट्स के लिए जो भी एयरप्लेनेंस है या
either come from Europe or the US,
तो यूरोप से आते हैं या फिर यूएस से आते
we do not have any company of our own which can
हैं हमारे पास खुद कोई कंपनी नहीं है जो
manufacture these airplanes.  China has already
यह एयरप्लेस बना पाए। चाइना ने ऑलरेडी
started the process of replacing Boeing 737 and other aircraft.
रिप्लेस करने का प्रोसेस शुरू कर दिया है।
Recently their C919 has
रिसेंटली जो इनका C919 है इसने काफी टेस्ट
also passed many tests.  However, it remains to be seen whether
भी पास कर लिए हैं। हालांकि देखना होगा कि
they will be able to make a plane that can compete with Boeing or
यह बोइंग के टक्कर का प्लेन बना पाएंगे या
not.  But China is
नहीं बना पाएंगे। बट चाइना इस बात को लेकर
quite clear that it does
काफी हद तक क्लियर है कि यह यूएस पर या
not want to depend on the US or Europe
फिर यूरोप पर डिपेंड नहीं करना चाहते अपनी
for its aircraft needs.  So now look,
एयरप्लेस की नीड के लिए। तो अभी तो देखिए
this crash will be studied and evaluated.
इस क्रैश को स्टडी किया जाएगा, इवैलुएट
What happened here?
किया जाएगा। यहां पर हुआ क्या है?
Actually, like in the South Korea case, there have been
एक्चुअली क्या साउथ कोरिया वाले केस की
a lot of bird hits here
तरह बहुत सारी बर्ड हिट्स हुई है यहां पर
or was there some engine issue?  I think whatever
या कुछ इंजन का इशू था। आई थिंक जो भी
result comes out here will be in the long term.
यहां पर रिजल्ट निकल के आता है लॉन्ग टर्म
Even in the field of civil aviation.  We
में। इवन इन द फील्ड ऑफ सिविल एिएशन। हमें
should properly focus on Make in India.  We should make airplanes.  We should have
चाहिए। वी शुड मेक एयरप्लेंस। वी शुड हैव
companies.  Where we can hold them accountable
कंपनीज़। जहां पे हम उनको अकाउंटेबल ठहरा
regarding the standards of airplanes.
पाएं एयरप्लेंस के स्टैंडर्ड को लेकर।
Because now let me tell you clearly, this
क्योंकि अब मैं आपको साफ-साफ बता दूं ये
thing has become clear.  It is not the case
बात क्लियर हो चुकी है। कुछ ऐसा नहीं है
that these planes are made in the US or if
कि ये प्लेन यूएस में बनते हैं अगर या फिर
some parts come from the US then they
यूएस से कुछ पार्ट्स आते हैं तो कुछ यह
become of very high quality.  Many
बहुत ज्यादा हाई क्वालिटी के हो गए। कई
Whistle Brokers have confirmed
विसल ब्रोर्स ने यह बात कंफर्म कर दी है
that these companies are using sub-standard parts in order to earn profits and increase the
कि यह कंपनियां प्रॉफिट के चक्कर में और
valuation of their shares.
अपने शेयर्स की जो वैल्यू्यूएशन है उसके
So somewhere there needs
कर रही हैं। तो कहीं ना कहीं देयर नीड्स
to be an Indian alternative.  If you agree with
टू बी एन इंडियन अल्टरनेटिव। अगर आप एग्री
me then share your
करते हैं मेरी बात से तो शेयर करिएगा अपने
thoughts in the comment section.  And on this note, the
थॉट्स कमेंट सेक्शन में। और इसी नोट के
video ends.  Thank you for
साथ यह है वीडियो का अंत। थैंक यू फॉर
listening.  And I always say that may the Gods
लिसनिसिंग। एंड आई ऑलवेज से मे द गॉड्स
watch over us and whatever victims are here,
वाच ओवर अस एंड जो भी यहां पर विक्टिम्स
hopefully they survive and there are
हैं होपफुली यह सर्वाइव कर पाए एंड ज्यादा
no more casualties here.
कैजुअल्टीज यहां पर ना हो।